Finding Aid for the Los Angeles Unified School District Board of Education Records LSC.1923
UCLA Library Special Collections
Los Angeles Unified School District Board of Education records
1875-2012
UCLA Library Special Collections
Los Angeles (Calif.). Board of Education
LSC.1923
1362.4 linear feet (2792 boxes)
The Los Angeles City Board of Education serves as the governing, policy-making body for the Los Angeles Unified School District (LAUSD). The collection spans from 1875-2012 and consists of Minutes books, Board and committee reports, administrative guides, annual reports, bulletins, classification reports, index cards, financial records, school and teacher directories, maps, publications and subject files.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Los Angeles Unified School District Board of Education, 2011 and 2015.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9969119863606533
Biography/History
The Los Angeles City Board of Education serves as the governing, policy-making body for the Los Angeles Unified School District (LAUSD), which was previously composed of three districts: the Los Angeles City School District that served kindergarten through 8th grade and formed on September 19, 1853; the Los Angeles City High School District that served grades 9 through 12 and formed in 1890; and the Los Angeles City Junior College District formed in 1931. As a result of the school unification election of June 7, 1960, the elementary and high school districts merged to form the LAUSD on July 1, 1961. Since July 1, 1969, the Los Angeles Junior College District has been governed by a separate Board of Trustees.
The first ordinance establishing public schools in Los Angeles was passed by the Common Council on July 25, 1853. This ordinance provided for the Council's appointment of three Commissioners of Public Schools to serve as a City Board of Education with the chairman to serve as the Superintendent of Schools.
At the next meeting of the Council, J. Lancaster Brent, Lewis Granger and Stephen C. Foster were appointed members of the Board of Education. J. Lancaster Brent served as chairman of the Board and Superintendent. Stephen C. Foster assumed the office of mayor in May 1854 and during his inaugural address, urged the necessity of increased school facilities as the city did not yet own a school building.
Foster recommended the building of two school houses, the revision of the ordinance governing the schools, and the appointment of a school superintendent and school marshal. At the next Council meeting, an ordinance was presented and passed, providing for the Council's appointment of three school trustees, a superintendent and a school marshal on the first Monday of June each year.
Before the close of the school year, School House No. 1, a two-story brick building located on the corner of Spring and Second streets was completed and opened on March 19, 1855. School House No. 2, a two-room building located at the junction of North Main and Los Angeles streets was built in 1856.
From 1853 to 1866 the Common Council appointed the members of the Board of Education and the school superintendents. From 1866 to 1870 the three member School Boards and the Superintendents were elected by popular vote at the city elections. In 1870 when it was discovered that there was no legal authority for the office of superintendent, this office ceased to exist from 1870 to 1873.
In 1872, a special act of the legislature created a City Board of Education, consisting of five members elected at large, and gave it the authority to appoint a superintendent of schools. Although not required, from 1873 to 1889 the Board members held partisan offices.
A new city charter adopted in 1889 authorized a nine-member Board, one member from each political ward of the city and the Board maintained its authority to appoint a superintendent. During the period of 1880-1890, the population of the city increased from 11,000 to 50,000.
After a period of general unrest and dissatisfaction with the ward system, charges of bribery were made against certain Board members during 1897-1898 and citizens demanded changes. As a result, the ward system was abolished in 1904 and a new city charter restored the at-large, non-partisan Board of Education and reduced its nine members to seven.
From 1904 to 1978, each member was chosen by the entire electorate of the LAUSD. Although during the latter years of this period, each Board member was assigned an Office number (Offices No. 1 through 7), the entire electorate still chose each member for each office.
With the passage of a City Charter Amendment, Proposition M on November 7, 1978, the District was divided into seven geographical areas or Districts. These Districts were also numbered 1 through 7 but did not coincide with the old Office numbers, nor was there any relation between the two.
The election for odd-numbered Districts was held in the spring of 1979 and members were seated July 1, 1979. The election for even-numbered Districts was held in the spring of 1981 and members were seated July 1, 1981. Thus, the term "Office" when used in connection with a Board of Education seat became obsolete with the beginning of the school year on July 1, 1981. Board of Education members were then spoken of as representing a numerically designated District.
Today the LAUSD is still governed by a seven-member Board of Education elected directly by voters of its seven Districts. Board members are elected for terms of four years and elections are held every other year with three members chosen at one election and four at the next. The Board appoints a Superintendent for a four-year term who serves as the chief executive officer of the Board and the school system.
The District encompasses approximately 710 square miles, includes virtually all of the City of Los Angeles, many other cities and several unincorporated areas of Los Angeles County. The LAUSD is the largest public school system in California based on pupil enrollment and the second largest public school district in the United States.
Scope and Content
The Los Angeles Unified School District Board of Education records range from 1875-2012. The collection consists of Minutes books, Board and committee reports, administrative guides, annual reports, bulletins, classification reports, index cards, financial records, school and teacher directories, maps, publications and research files.
The first series, Minutes, and the third series, Subject Files, comprise the bulk of the collection. The Minutes (also called Board Reports) span 137 years and are the District's official record of business. The Subject Files cover 759 subjects and are records that serve as supporting documentation for the Minutes.
The Board Secretariat or Executive Officer of the Board, formerly the Clerk of the Board, was responsible for the stewardship of these records. The Board Secretariat's File and Minutes Units maintained these records for use by the Superintendent, Board members, District staff and the public.
The enduring value of the LAUSD Board of Education records lies within the evidential and informational records maintained by the Board. These records contain historical evidence of the Board's organization, functions, policies, decisions, procedures, and operations which speak to the origins of its existence, its work and achievements. These records provide essential information on all matters with which the Board dealt including staff, students, parents, organizations, land matters, politics, events, programs, war emergencies, natural disasters and civil unrest.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Minutes, 1875-2009
Series 2: Annexed School Districts' Minutes and Ledgers, 1889-1932
Series 3: Subject Files, 1913-2012
Series 4: Personnel, 1921-2000
Series 5: Index Cards, circa 1875-1997
Series 6: Budget, circa 1935-2008
Series 7: Rules and Regulations, 1898-2010
Series 8: Bulletins, 1923-2010
Series 9: Superintendent's Annual Reports, 1903-1955
Series 10: Classification Reports, 1926-1984
Series 11: Publications, 1884-2009
Related Material
Forty Years in Education in Southern California (1904-1944) [oral history transcript] / Arthur Gould, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1965. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
I'm Home Free [oral history transcript] / Ellis A. Jarvis, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1966. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Interview of James Taylor [oral history transcript] / James Taylor, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 2010. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Interview of Owen Knox [oral history transcript] / Owen Knox, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 2008. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Interview of Rita Walters [oral history transcript] / Rita Walters, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 2011. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Interview of Sidney Thompson [oral history transcript] / Sidney Thompson, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 2011. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
American Civil Liberties Union of Southern California Records (Collection 900). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Augustus F. Hawkins Papers (Collection 1642). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Paul Egly Papers (Collection 1282). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Los Angeles School Monitoring Committee (Collection 1291). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Helene V. Smookler Papers on School Integration (Collection 1547). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Julian Nava Papers (Collection 400). Chicano Studies Research Center, University of California, Los Angeles.
Separated Material
Records before 1875, called the Common Council Minutes, were not part of this accession, and are kept by the Los Angeles City Records Center and Archives at the Piper Technical Center at 555 Ramirez St, #320, Los Angeles, CA 90012.
School districts -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Los Angeles Unified School District -- Archives.; Los Angeles (Calif.). -- Board of Education -- Archives.
- Minutes, 1875-2009
  Scope and Content
  The Board Minutes are the Los Angeles Unified School District's official record of business transacted during regular, special and closed session meetings. Regular Board Minutes reflect a standard Order of Business which shifts over time but historically occurs in the following order: Roll Call of Members, Approval of Minutes, Reports from Standing and Special Committees, Special Reports from the Superintendent, Communications and Petitions, Miscellaneous Business and Adjournment. Noticed motions and resolutions are voted upon by the Board and when carried, result in the creation of District policy. In addition to regular meeting Minutes, the Board generates Minutes for its special meetings which are open to the public and agendas for its closed sessions. Annual meetings are held on July 1st of each year during which the Board elects one of its members as President whose term of office continues for one year or until a successor is elected. At the annual meeting, the Board President designates the standing committees for the year. Standing committees change over time with the Board's shifting functions and priorities. For example, in 1964 the President appointed a chairman and two other members to each of the following standing committees: Budget and Finance, Building, Cafeterias, Insurance, Law and Rules, Personnel and Schools, Purchasing, Transportation and the Committee of the Whole which consists of all Board members.
  The Minutes include the following documents as attachments: Census Marshal's Reports, Controller's Annual Financial Reports, bond election returns, Communications and Reports from Standing Committees, Ad-Hoc Committees, Superintendents and speakers who address the Board.
  - Los Angeles Unified School District, 1875 May 19-2009 June 23
    - Volume A Board of Education Minutes, 1875 May 19-1880 November (Box 831)
      Board meetings held in the rooms of the Commercial Bank or at Board members' residences and offices. Board President M. Kremer called the May 19, 1875 meeting to order with Board members Alfred James, Dr. Joseph Kurtz, Dr. J.P. Widney and Secretary W.T. Lucky present and H.D. Barrows absent.
      On June 25, 1875, the Board carried a motion to change the salary of the teacher of the colored school from $70 to $80 a month. At a special meeting on December 18, 1875, Mr. James suggested that rules be adopted for regular transactions of business and formed a committee of one to study this issue. On January 13, 1876, the Board adopted its rules and carried a motion to support drafting a bill to be forwarded to Sacramento to enable the Board to issue bonds. On February 11, 1876, the Board carried a resolution concerning "houses of ill repute" in the vicinity of the Bath Street School. On August 17, 1876, due to overcrowding of public schools, the Board resolved to exclude all pupils who are not residing within the District's limits. On April 5, 1879, the Board received a communication concerning misappropriation of funds by the Vernon School District. On August 18, 1879, the Board discussed salaries of certificated teachers. On March 6, 1880, the Board moved that the Committee on Discipline examine conditions of two overcrowded schools. On March 15, 1880, the Board adopted a resolution to allow the Trustees of the State Normal School use of rooms in the High School to accommodate a branch of the Normal School until a building is erected. On July 19, 1880, the Board elected Mrs. C.B. Jones as Superintendent of the Public Schools of the City. On August 7, 1880, Mrs. C.B. Jones was also assigned Principal of the High School Building.
    - Volume B Board of Education Minutes, 1880 December-1885 September 26 (Box 832)
      During a Saturday meeting in December 1880, the Board carried a motion to discontinue the colored school at the end of the current term. On October 25, 1881, the Board received a legal opinion as to its power to purchase property and build school houses. On January 12, 1882, President Brousseau announced the following four standing committees for the new year: Finance, Supplies and Repairs, Teachers and Visiting Schools and Library. On June 5, 1882, the Board carried its custom of promotion of scholars from lower to higher grades with 75 percent as the standard for promotion. These "Rules and Standards of Promotion" are described in the December 22, 1883 Minutes. On July 3, 1882, the Board received communication from the Clerk of the Council offering use of the Council rooms for Board meetings. On September 6, 1883, the Superintendent reported enrollment of pupils to date: 2,400. During a special session on September 3, 1884, the Superintendent was authorized to redistrict the City for the Board. On December 3, 1884, the Board adopted its governing rules and regulations. The September 11, 1885 Minutes include the newsclipping, "City Schools: A New Division of the School Districts" which describes schools by district and includes attendance boundaries and names of principals.
    - Volume C Board of Education Minutes, 1885 September 8-1889 March 21 (Box 833)
      On November 14, 1885, the Board received a petition of 53 teachers praying for the abolition of morning and afternoon recesses. On December 21, 1885, the Committee on Rules and Regulations reported on a conference with City Attorney J.W. McKinley concerning the necessary restrictions for the prevention of contagious diseases in the public schools. On April 6, 1886, a resolution was presented and read with no response or action taken by the Board, asking the School Department's cooperation in ridding the City of the Chinese, a curse to youth in immorality. On May 17, 1886, the Board met in special session to arrange the move of Central School house in whole or in part. On September 18, 1886, the Secretary was instructed to ask the Chief of Police to station a policeman at the Central Building while it was being moved across Temple Street. On February 12, 1887, the Board discussed amendments to the Charter which would be more beneficial to the School Department than those proposed by the City Council. On September 27, 1887, the Secretary was directed to correspond with the Secretary of the San Francisco School Board concerning the manner of conducting night schools so that Los Angeles may establish its own. On January 17, 1888, the Secretary was instructed to notify the City Council that the Board is in need of funds because the Council does not provide money on the Bonds already voted on by the people. On April 3, 1888, a verbal communication was offered with reference to the establishment of separate schools for the District's 75 colored pupils. On April 3, 1888, the Superintendent reported the total enrollment for March at 5,475 with an average daily attendance of 4,524.
    - Volume 1 Board of Education Minutes, 1889 March 21-1893 January 3 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      The Board approved the election of teachers without discrimination based on sex. Mr. A.E. Pomeroy was elected President on March 21, 1889. Building and Finance Committees discussed the necessity of school bonds. The Board approved the July 1, 1889 resolution in favor of resident teachers. The Board approved high school subject segregation. The Library Committee discussed incorporation of the school library into the city library.
    - Volume 2 Board of Education Minutes, 1893 January 3-1897 May 24 (Box 2)
      The Board approved high school course of study changes, a Resolution on married ladies, and a Resolution for City Council to pass an ordinance prohibiting saloons from opening within 500 feet of school buildings and requested "laws to abate this social evil." The Board discussed issuing and calling elections for school bonds.
    - Volume 3 Board of Education Minutes, 1897 June 14-1898 June 27 (Box 3)
      The Board discussed charges against employees, deaf children's oral education, entertainment in school buildings, Sloyd Tools purchases, and sending representatives to the National Educational Association Convention. The La Fiesta Committee reported against school children's participation. Superintendent Foshay was authorized to attend the National Teacher's Association Convention.
    - Volume 4 Board of Education Minutes, 1898 July 11-1899 November 6 (Box 4)
      The City Attorney presented an opinion on the bond issue and the Board discussed bond elections. The Board decided to establish a school for deaf children. The Board discussed District boundaries and deeds for school property. The Board granted permission for girls to attend Spring Street Night School with boys. The Board adopted text books and periodicals purchased for use by high school teachers and pupils.
    - Volume 5 Board of Education Minutes, 1899 November 13-1901 April 13 (Box 5)
      The Board discussed building sites and bonds. The Board asked the City Council to issue bond funding to purchase sites, erect buildings and furnish schools. The Board approved the purchase of a library accessions book and a course of study resolution. A Board discussion favored the entire Board visiting schools.
    - Volume 6 Board of Education Minutes, 1901 April 24-1902 December 10 (Box 6)
      The Board created the Assistant Superintendent's office, discussed District boundary changes, ordered three hundred High School diplomas, established a Kindergarten at University School, authorized a Librarian for the High School, and approved pay for teachers quarantined for health reasons.
    - Volume 7 Board of Education Minutes, 1902 December 23-1904 September 12 (Box 7)
      The Board approved the schools' observance of Arbor Day, discussed the enactment of Compulsory Education Law, the opening of a parental school in conjunction with the Detention Home, redistricting and the idea of high school students living outside the city to pay tuition to cover maintenance. The Juvenile Court Board requested that the Detention House be kept open in the summer and the Board request to the Police Commission for an on call officer was denied due to shortage of officers.
    - Volume 8 Board of Education Minutes, 1904 September 19-1905 June 1 (Box 8)
      The Board unanimously carried the motion for departmental horses. The Board discussed the dangers of ice cream vendors to school children. The Board ordered a map of city and adopted rules regarding quorum. The School Census Marshal's Report is included in this volume.
    - Volume 9 Board of Education Minutes, 1905 June 10-1908 April 25 (Box 9)
      The Board discussed annexation, advertising in schools, boundary lines of school districts and orders of Annual Reports. The Board moved to elect M.C. Bettinger as Assistant Superintendent. Superintendent Foshay resigned. The Board decided that high schools be districted by the Superintendent. The Board carried resolutions on bond issues, Spring Street property and the subway under Olive Street. The Board decided to establish truant schools and examine teachers by Committee and Superintendent.
    - Volume 10 Board of Education Minutes, 1908 April 27-1910 June 29 (Box 10)
      M.C. Bettinger was elected the first Assistant Superintendent for a term of four years. Principal of Polytechnic High School, John H. Francis was appointed Superintendent for a four year term. The Board held a Special Election for School Bonds.
    - Volume 11 Board of Education Minutes, 1910 July 11-1912 April 25 (Box 11)
      The Board discussed salary schedules, number of teachers, average daily attendance, cost per pupil, the wrecking of Utah Street School, bids and the decision that the recently enacted 8 hours law does not apply to janitresses.
    - Volume 12 L.A. City School District Minutes, 1912 May 2-1913 May 22 (Box 12)
      The Board received Communication from Parent-Teacher Associations. On May 22, 1913, the Board discussed section 308b of the California State Penal Code, "Any teacher, principal, employee or school official who doesn't use the prescribed text books in elementary or secondary schools is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction shall be charged a fine of not more than 100 dollars."
    - Volume 13 L.A. City School District Minutes, 1913 May 29-1914 June 3 (Box 13)